when he first like hit the scene it was
like grainy videos of him lifting
unbelievable weights at like 17 years
old you put a treadmill at a 12 incline
and 3 mph and you walk on it for 30
minutes seems simple and boring right
I'll be honest with you this kind of
revolutionized my Approach if you're not
as hyped as could be for the heaviest
weight ever lifted off the floor I don't
know what I don't know what gets you
[Music]
excited welcome to strength weekly the
weekly youtube/ social media /gen
internet show that keeps you updated on
everything from the barbell game I'm
David Thomas toown and I am joined by
the Intrepid the incomparable and the
very strong Philip blechman all right
first off Olivia Reeves in the 71 kgam
category at the iwf Grand Prix in Doha
puts on one of the best performances in
recent USA weightlifting memory and
actually scores the heaviest cleaning
jerk for a nons super heavyweight
American woman ever which is something
really cool Carlos Nasser of Bulgaria
comes back from a gnarly injury and does
seemingly The Impossible puts himself
right back into the Paris Olympics
conversation when most folks thought he
would be out for potentially years
really amazing story there then we have
the heaviest deadlift of all time 505 kg
who did that why did they do that how
did they do that we've got that
information and more and then finally
one of my favorite things to talk about
12330 it's not just a social media fad
anymore it might actually
work before we get to that make sure you
subscribe to barbend on YouTube and
social platforms we either at barbend or
barbend news on pretty much every social
platform give us a follow it'll make us
feel good about ourselves we could all
use that get in the holiday spirit Phil
which of our stories today are you
personally most excited about you know
it's nice that we have a fully fully
stacked show uh but if you're not if if
you're not at as hyped as could be for
the heaviest weight ever lifted off the
floor I don't know what I don't know
what gets you excited you know okay okay
calm calm it down Phil too much
excitement too too much excitement have
some have some decaf coffee that's all
decaf that's a giant pot of decaf that's
all GI f a Dap let's dive in at the iwf
Grand Prix in Doha cutter Olivia Reeves
lifting us a 71 kilogram athlete puts on
a performance for the Aegis goes six for
six sets more Junior World Records then
we can count yeah she's still a junior
and just so happens to clean and jerk
the heaviest weight ever for a nons
super heavyweight American woman and by
the way it's not like she's in the
weight class below super heavyweight
she's a few weight classes down so
really impressive performance Phil you
want to give us uh her kind of tail of
the tape for the day I would love to
give us Olivia Reeves tail of tail of
the tape so in the snatch she hit 115 kg
that's a junior world record in the
clean and jerk she scored 147 kg that's
a junior world record and for the total
that capped out to 262 kg guess what a
junior world record the most important
thing to keep in mind is it establishes
her as the oddson favorite to qualify
for the Paris Olympics in one of the
most stacked weight categories in
American Olympic history now she's
lifting as a 71 kilogram athlete Phil
who is trailing behind her in the
American system so right behind her are
also well-known names that our audience
will likely recognize as Meredith alwine
and Kate Viber Davis both of them are
also in the running for sure at the 2024
games the quota for athletes uh in
weightlifting was decreased so it is
going to be pretty strategic on each
country to put forth who they actually
think is their best lifter in each
category because they were only allowed
to put forth one so this this is not a
chance that you will not see multiple
athletes from the same country on the
podium it's it's going to be a tight
race but that's that's what happens with
all of the
drug testing that went down but
hopefully that changes in 2028 but for
2024 it's going to be a smaller athlete
quota and Reeves is now in the lead yeah
uh still a lot of lifting to go between
now and Paris but we will be keeping our
eyes on it and for me this is probably
the most exciting story and the most
exciting race for Olympic qualification
uh among the among American athletes I I
think it's almost almost hands down that
that's the case well let's move on to
another impressive and maybe borderline
inspiring weightlifting story uh Carlos
Nasser of Bulgaria uh Phil give us the
quick Cliff Notes if you don't mind on
who this dude is yeah so he's a
19-year-old Bulgarian uh weightlifter
who I mean whenever this guy has a
barbell in his hands you expect
something Monumental to happen is what
it seems like every time he's on camera
so uh he competed in the 89 kilogram
class at the iwf Grand Prix in Cutter
and he lifted 223 kg which for those who
don't know what that number means that's
1 kogam over the previous world record
held by CH tantau so it was a Monumental
lift this guy Naser is like was the
Young Gun and was really on track to
kind of be the favorite at least the
most exciting lifter in this category
when it came to Paris and Paris
qualification going to that last period
of Paris qualification in may he hurts
as Achilles Achilles injuries for
weightlifters uh they can sideline them
that's career threatening almost it's
career it is career threatening he came
back in the same calendar year comes
back wins his Grand Prix against some
stiff competition and by the way sets a
new clean and jerk world record and
amazingly puts himself back in pole
position as the guy to beat in this
weight category just a few months after
we assumed he was going to be a
non-factor in Paris uh Phil I can't
actually think of another story quite
like this in we recent weightlifting
memory I still recall when he first like
hit the scene it was like grainy videos
of him lifting unbelievable weights at
like 17 years old and then he comes in
at 18 he's now like a notable name he
then gets injured he comes back less
than a year later and he's setting this
Mark of a a kilogram above the world
record just for for posterity is uh the
rest of the tale of his tape was he
snatched 170 kg and he hit a 390 K 393
kg total which did her earn him the
overall gold in addition to that
deadlift world record so and one thing
to also note dude is still a junior
lifter he's not even
20 I I what was I doing what were we
doing at 19 I was probably having
cookies or something I was definitely
eating cookies but doing a lot of other
stuff not appropriate for this recording
uh I want to point out that he took that
world record back from Tien of China uh
who some people have speculated there's
been rers on the internet that Tian is
my cousin and I'm just going to say
right now I have no proof to the
contrary right but if it is true if it
is true that we are related however
distantly it's pretty clear he got
different genes than I did uh because uh
your boy don't lift like that your boy
don't big exclusive it's a big exclusive
David big exclusive we both have good
hair tant's got some flow and mine's a
little curlier I just got a haircut uh
but you know we both you know like this
maybe maybe the S the similarity between
me and tantau is like from the forehead
up not from certainly not in the
musculature and weightlifting ability
from the neck Down's luckily if you want
to join the top ranks though you just
can LOF the hair off a little bit
further and drop a weight class and that
will help your lifts uh I actually did
that actually did that uh once when I
was lifting
anyway Phil I'm going to just like toss
this one up this is going to be the
softest of Aly oops because we're going
to transition from weightlifting to
powering strongman we don't really know
because this was
unofficial it's not a world record
because this lift that we're going to
talk about is unofficial in both
strongman and powerlifting competition
however the heaviest deadlift of all
time off the ground 55
kilograms just happen and that's big
news it might be why you're still
watching at this point in the broadcast
let's be honest
Phil what was the waight who done pulled
it
how did they done pull it and why is it
important on December 2nd 2023 venceslav
demitro deadlifted 505 kg which is
1,113 lb that's a lot of weight at the
2023 eisenhart black competition in
Bavaria now what does that mean that
means that he lifted four kilos over
what was the previously he heaviest ever
pull by haor bjen well-known strongman
coming back to the Arnold strongman
classic in 24 that'll be big news so the
record goes 500 kg as Eddie Hall in 2016
strongman to 501 kilograms that's haor
bonon just to one up Eddie Hall
essentially literally oneup and then ven
slav comes out of nowhere now this guy
he's lifted in Sumo he was wearing
lifting straps it's not an official lift
we get it it's entirely different from
the fact that uh Hall and bjornson who
are also in the 500 kilogram Club lifted
in in in uh conventional stances but the
fact that a human can lift this amount
is still noteworthy by every metric yes
the range of motion isn't as much as a
conventional deadlift yes he was wearing
lifting straps and it wasn't raw yes it
wasn't drug tested we don't know what
was going on necessarily he lifted the
most ever okay the most ever 505
kilograms it's
unbelievable so you're channeling some
Stephen A Smith there I absolutely love
it it's it's Preposterous it's
Blasphemous how much weight this guy
lifted off the ground okay that's
exciting and you know what he's an
athlete that I really didn't have on my
radar to be honest with you like did
anybody did anybody that's the thing did
anybody I mean he like you go over to a
social media dude's been lifting 450
kilograms 465 kilograms like the weight
that he's pulling off the
ground he's he's he's casually doing
these list I mean yes he's using Texas
barbells or whatever so they have more
Bend and the range of motion isn't
necessary but like dude's locking this
stuff out he's locking it out okay it's
heavy it's heavy he's a guy who livs
heavy that's the news David he's a guy
who lifts
heavy you killed my segue fil no it's
fine I was going to say well let's lock
it out and get to our final segment of
the day how's that for an awkward
transition that was beautiful David to
I'm here to make it weird all day David
Thomas to we're gonna talk about our
strength tip of the week which isn't
really a a strength tip but more of a
health cardio leaning out don't lose
your gains tip right so this is
something that I talk about about way
too much and everyone tells me to shut
up we're going to talk about 12330 the
social media cardio phenomenon that
might actually be one of the best things
for strength athletes and here's what it
is you put a treadmill at a 12 incline
and three miles per hour and you walk on
it for 30 minutes seems simple and
boring right I'll be honest with you
this kind of revolutionized my approach
to to Wellness in many ways I love
lifting weights not the biggest cardio
fan I'm always one of those folks who's
like I'll just lift weights faster I
think 12330 is something that started on
social media I want to get the name
right Lauren Geraldo who is a an
Instagram influencer posted about kind
of coming across and gradually
developing this this protocol to get in
shap to lose weight right for fat loss
but it's something that's actually I'm
not going to say catching on like
wildfire in the strength Community but
gradually catching on in the strength
Community someone who I know who's a
real big proponent of this is maybe
someone who might be an unlikely
proponent of this Bobby Maximus former
UFC fighter he was involved with Jim
Jones he's like someone who Men's Health
called one of the 100 fittest guys of
all time he's like a fitness OG and when
I see Bobby Maximus saying and posting
on social like hey I love 12330 actually
give it a go it's an amazing way to stay
lean to help you stay lean to work on
cardiovascular health to promote
recovery because even strength athletes
proof cardiovascular health there's a
lot of evidence that's actually going to
help you with your strength gains and
you're not going to walk off your gains
see Bobby Maximus posting about this I'm
like oh hold on there might be something
here there might be something here Phil
you've got some interesting research
queued up
about 12330 and how it actually might be
impactful for people who like lifting
heavy how can walking like this be
important for people who like picking up
heavy things well first and foremost all
of the re all of the research to date
right now suggests that consistency is
more important than literally anything
else so being able to do 12 330 and stay
consistent with doing that over and over
like throughout the week constantly that
is the way that you actually get to the
results that you want over the long term
so being able to have a program that's
simple as 12330 that you can be
consistent with that's the biggest
Factor uh for people who aren't
accustomed to this kind of cardio and uh
you jump right in you're like oh man 12
is too much or three is too fast at 12
or 30 minutes is too much at that rate
one thing that is also useful uh getting
a heart rate monitor can help because
all the research suggest that for this
kind of walking on a treadmill that the
perceived exertion is more than the
actual exertion you're putting on your
body because it is low impact cardio and
so if you have a heart rate monitor that
you can notice where your heart rate is
elevated to and you can sort of gauge
that to get up to the 12330 standard and
then use that as consistency but like if
you feel as though when you start this
that it is wow this is way more
difficult than you expected it to be
that is likely just how you are
perceiving its difficulty rather rather
than it's actual difficulty on your body
that's just a matter of getting your rep
your reps in effectively and doing it
over time and then you will gradually
get to that pretty quickly so uh that's
one thing so the rate of perceived
exertion on this is probably higher than
the actual toll on your body if you have
not if you're not accustomed to it the
second thing is the way that your knees
position themselves while you're walking
in an incline is likely to reduce pain
on your knee joint so this kind of 12
330 walking on an incline healthy for
your knees that's great to know for
those for for people who can't run or it
hurts to run on a treadmill or do any
other kind of cardio and the other last
thing that I want to point out for this
is for people who are getting into 123
30 as we get older research has shown
that when you're walking on an incline
you naturally favor your dominant side
to help you offset any difficulty
walking up that hill so be mindful as
you're doing 12330 to not to to keep
your gate uh neutral and not lead
towards your dominant side the research
has shown that people who are right leg
dominant are going to are more likely to
be susceptible to this so something to
keep in mind as we uh get into 12330
which David and I are both proponents of
that is also what I like to do for
cardio because it is not difficult you
can put something on your phone or watch
the TV while you're you're getting your
cardio in and most importantly you keep
those Gates and you you run through
podcasts if you got a backl the
broadcast you want to listen to there's
no better way to get through that the
other thing I want to point out too uh
don't grab the handlebars on the
treadmill right like it's very you could
do it subconsciously it's very tempting
to just like lean you know like put your
arms on the sides or like lean over
don't do that don't grab the treadmill
right those are there for safety if you
slip or something like that don't don't
do that you don't need those you don't
need those you can do it without you can
do it you can work up to it right um
other thing I want to say about 12330 I
know consistency is important I try to
do this with some consistency uh it is
the best thing ever for me when it comes
to shaking off travel rust whether youve
just kind of like been cooped up on an
airplane for a while or you have jet lag
or something I love this I'm my big
proponent getting an early workout in
that's not too difficult kind of as soon
as you land or soon soon after you
arrive somewhere after plane travel or
automobile travel or train travel Planes
Trains automobiles what is the time of
year so yeah those are some tips there
anyway Phil and I big fans of
12330 and uh let us know your thoughts
in the comments let us know if you love
it hate it and let us know if you just
hate us but
Phil that brings us to the end of this
week's strength weekly um I'm going to
express a little gratitude because it's
that time of year Phil I'm grateful for
you I'm grateful to you I love this this
is one one one of the high points of my
week recording with you buddy it is a
mutual gratefulness and David now that
we know that your uh extended family
goes into Elite lifters I look forward
to your 506 kg deadlift
attempt there will be an attempt there
will be an attempt love to try love to
try until then we're strength weekly
brought to you by barbend thanks so much
for tuning
[Music]
in